Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551 10 Center Dr Bethesda, MD 20892

🛮 simon.liu@nih.gov - 🗏 nhgri/mgb

Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate IRTA fellow at the National Institutes of Health interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to public and private datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators. I am a member of the Medical Genomics Unit at the National Human Genome Research Institute.

Education

B.S., Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD. Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science

Honors: Upsilon Pi Epsilon, general honors, Dean's list

GPA: 3.69

Research Experience

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present With Benjamin Solomon

08/2017 - 05/2021

J-2

J-1

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, 02/2020 - 05/2021 MD, USA.

With Chad Gordon.

Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [award] [news]

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA. 07/2018 - 03/2020 With Junfang Wu

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 12/2018 - 03/2020 With Susan Hutfless

Research Assistant, Battle Lab, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.

acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267-283.

02/2018 - 09/2018

With Alexis Battle and Ben Strober

Publications

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Publons.

Journal Articles

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., Liu, S., Li, H., Stoica, B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376-11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199 Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., Liu, S., Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltagegated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005

Conference Papers

Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., Liu, S., Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, C-1 J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-quided colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging 2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020). https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873

Meeting Abstracts

Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., Liu, S., & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in A-2 outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314 Hutfless, S. M., Chen, P.-H., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., Liu, S., A-1 Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name

In Submission Ledgister Hanchard, S.*, Dwyer, M.C.*, Liu, S.*, Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Scoping review and classification of deep learning in medical genetics. [In submission]. *Equal contributions.	P-2
Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. L., Liu, S. , Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2022). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes. Frontiers in Genetics. [Accepted]	P-1
Selected Honors Linda Trinh Memorial Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA	05/2021
COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shields With Y. Bai, J. Feitelberg, K. Hu, S. Kumar, K. Leo, J. Li, C. Shallal, and N. Zhang	
Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up , Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	12/2020
Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray. [report] [ppt] [award] With F. Shao, Y. Huang, and A. Harmalkar.	
Provost's Undergraduate Research Award , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device With Chad Gordon. [award] [news]	11/2020
Upsilon Pi Epsilon, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	10/2020
International Honor Society for the Computing and Information Disciplines	
Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.	06/2017
Selected Press Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input Mag. February 18, 2022.	2022
Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019.	2019
Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News-Letter. November 15, 2018.	2018
Entrepreneurship Head of Manufacturing, Health 3D, LLC, Baltimore, MD, USA. 04/2	2018 - 05/2021
Built up manufacturing arm and online presence of healthcare education venture. Selected into Social Innovation Lab 2018-2019 Cohort and Spring 2020 FUEL Accelerator Cohort. Oversaw manufacturing pipeline of COVID-19 PPE for the Johns Hopkins Health System [article].	
Teaching Course Assistant, Gateway Computing: Python, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Led workshops and weekly office hours Graded students' projects and provided feedback Held individual and group review sessions	2020, Sp 2021

smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology,

Selected Coursework

Undergraduate

Computer Integrated Surgery I Computer Integrated Surgery II Machine Learning Machine Learning: Deep Learning Neuroengineering Lab

Cell and Tissue Engineering Lab Biomedical Data Science Precision Care Medicine I Precision Care Medicine II

Computational Medicine: Cardiology Computational Medicine: Cardiology Lab

 $\label{prop:conditions} Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics$

Metadata

This document lives online at simonliu.dev/markdown-cv/.

A downloadable version can be found at simonliu.dev/files/liu_cv.pdf.

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp. MIT License.

Last updated: March 2022